Arthur Meyer Papers 5252
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Arthur Meyer Papers
1918-1950
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Meyer, Arthur
5252
4 cubic feet
4 linear ft.
Articles, case files, proceedings, speeches (documents).
Include speeches and articles by Meyer (1941-1950); his correspondence while on the U.S. National War Labor Board (1942-1945); and excerpts from letters written by Meyer (1942-1955). Also materials on the Fact-Finding Committee of the Board of Education, City of New York (1951); transcripts and accompanying documentation regarding the National War Labor Board case of the Electrical Transcription Manufacturing Company vs. the American Federation of Musicians (1942-1943); and miscellaneous arbitration case files (1942-1946).
2294674
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, October 11, 2000
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, February 22, 2017
Biographical / Historical
Arthur S. Meyer was a member of the New York State Board of Mediation from its inception in 1937. In 1940, he was appointed as its chairman, a position in which he served until his retirement in 1950. Before becoming a mediator, Meyer was a successful businessman, rising to the posts of president and director of the Schulte Real Estate Company and vice-president of the Schulte Retail Stores Corporation. In 1942, Meyer was named chairman of a U.S. War Labor Board panel to rule on the demands of the Steel Workers Organizing Committee for a raise of one dollar per day and union security. The recommendation of Meyer and his committee formed the basis for a subsequent Board ruling known as the "Little Steel Formula".
Scope and Contents
Include speeches and articles by Meyer (1941-1950); his correspondence while on the U.S. National War Labor Board (1942-1945); and excerpts from letters written by Meyer (1942-1955). Also materials on the Fact-Finding Committee of the Board of Education, City of New York (1951); transcripts and accompanying documentation regarding the National War Labor Board case of the Electrical Transcription Manufacturing Company vs. the American Federation of Musicians (1942-1943); and miscellaneous arbitration case files (1942-1946).
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5111: New York City Board of Education Fact Finding Committee Report 5231: Arthur S. Meyer Papers 6045: Arthur S. Meyer Additional Files and Scrapbooks
Arbitration, Industrial -- Teachers -- New York (State) -- New York; Arbitration, Industrial -- United States -- Cases; Collective bargaining -- United States; Employment stabilization -- United States; Guaranteed annual wage -- United States; Industrial productivity -- United States; Industrial relations -- United States; Manpower planning -- United States; Mediation and conciliation, Industrial -- United States -- Cases; Open and closed shop -- United States; Strikes and lockouts -- United States -- Public opinion; Labor unions -- United States -- Political activity; Wages and labor productivity -- United States; War and emergency powers -- United States; Arbitration, Industrial -- Clothing industry -- United States; Arbitration, Industrial -- Construction industry -- United States; Arbitration, Industrial -- Electric industries -- United States; Arbitration, Industrial -- Musicians -- United States; Arbitration, Industrial -- Telecommunication -- United States; Collective bargaining -- Charities -- United States; Contracting out -- Arbitration, Industrial -- United States; Employees, Transfer of -- Arbitration, Industrial -- United States; Industry wide bargaining -- United States; Layoffs -- Arbitration, Industrial -- United States; Management rights -- Arbitration, Industrial -- United States; Open and closed shop -- Arbitration, Industrial -- United States; Position classification -- Arbitration, Industrial -- United States; Strikes and lockouts -- Coal mining industry -- United States; Strikes and lockouts -- Merchant marine -- United States; Strikes and lockouts -- Trucking industry -- United States; Teachers -- Salaries, etc. -- New York (State) -- New York; Union security -- Law and legislation -- United States; Union security -- United States; Unemployment -- Arbitration, Industrial -- United States; Wages -- Arbitration, Industrial -- United States; Wages -- Electric industries -- United States; Wages -- Metal-workers -- United States; Davis, William H.; Ellickson, Katherine Pollak, 1905-1996.; Feinsinger, Nathan Paul, 1902-1983.; Fly, James Lawrence; Frumesman, Harry; Gellhorn, Walter, 1906-1995; Herzog, Paul M., 1906-1986; Hilger, William S.; Jacobs, Arthur; Latimer, Murray Webb; McManus, Thomas P.; Meyer, Arthur S. (Arthur Simon), 1880-1955.; Miller, Max J.; Rubin, Milton.; Petrillo, James C. (James Caesar), 1892-1984; Podway, Joseph A.; Rubin, W. (George William), 1901-1972.; Thompson, Samuel H.; Waldron, William A.; Warren, Edgar F.; American Cloak and Suit Manufacturers Association, Inc.; American Communications Association; American Federation of Musicians; Congress of Industrial Organizations (U.S.); Electrical Transcription Manufacturers; General Electric Company; International Brotherhood of Teamsters, Chauffeurs, Warehousemen, and Helpers of America; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union; International Union of Operating Engineers; Laborers' International Union of North America; New York (N.Y.). Board of Education. Fact-Finding Committee; New York (State). Board of Mediation; New York Telephone Company; Press Wireless, Inc.; Transcontinental Gas Pipe Lines Corporation; United Association of Journeymen and Apprentices of the Plumbing and Pipefitting Industry; United Electrical, Radio, and Machine Workers of America; United States. National War Labor Board (1942-1945); United Telephone Organizations; Westinghouse Electric Corporation
2294674
- Official Report of Proceedings before the National War Labor Board of the Office for Emergency Management in the matter of Electrical Transcription Mfg. and the American Federation of Musicians, AFL, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Members: Vleyer, Chr. Representing the public; Gilbert E. Fuller-Industry Rep; Max Zaritsky-Labor Rep; Paul R. Hays-Counsel to the Panel; N.P. Feinsinger-Special Assistant to Panel
- Case no.111-2499-D Transcript volume 1, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Septmeber 7, 1943. pp.1-148
- Case no.111-2499-D Transcript volume 2, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Septmeber 8, 1943. pp.149-252
- Case no.111-2499-D Transcript volume 3, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Septmeber 9, 1943. pp.253-419
- Case no.111-2499-D Transcript volume 4, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Septmeber 20, 1943. pp.420-434
- Case no.111-2499-D Transcript volume 5, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Septmeber 21, 1943. pp.434-448
- Case no.111-2499-D Transcript volume 6, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Septmeber 27, 1943. pp.449-467
- Case no.111-2499-D Transcript volume 7, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Septmeber 28, 1943. pp.468-605
- Case no.111-2499-D Transcript volume 8, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  October 20, 1943. pp.606-616
- Case no.111-2499-D Transcript volume 9, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  November 3, 1943. pp.617-819
- Case no.111-2499-D Transcript volume 10, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  November 4, 1943. pp.820-915
- Case no.111-2499-D Transcript volume 11, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  November 5, 1943. pp.916-1137
- Case no.111-2499-D Transcript volume 12, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  November 9, 1943. pp.1138-1345
- Case no.111-2499-D Transcript volume 13, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  November 19, 1943. pp.1346-1560
- Case no.111-2499-D Transcript volume 14, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  November 20, 1943. pp.1561-1663
- Case no.111-2499-D Transcript volume 15, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  November 22, 1943. pp.1664-1900
- National Association of Broadcasters' Special American Federation of Musicians' Bulletins, 1942-1943 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Notes regarding Case no.111-2499-D, 1942-1943 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  Silver Anniversary Souvenir (1943) St. Louis Municipal Opera; Questionnaire concerning phonograph records, electrical transcriptions and musicians, put out by USA- Federal Communications Commissions; Statement of Joseph A. Podway (Counsel for AFM) at Senate Committee Hearing; Statement of James Lawrence Fly (Chairman, FCC) before the sub-committee on Interstate Commerce on 5 Res. 286, 77th Congress, 2nd session, Fly is Chairman of the Federal Communications Commission and the Board of War Communications i.e. the impact of the recording ban on the radio broadcast industry; Photostats of abstracts of court cases from various legal-reporting services (published) RCA Mfg. Co. Inc. v. Whiteman et. al. #357 Circuit Court of Appeals, 2nd Circuit, from the 114 Federal Reporter, 2d (series) 1940. Waring v. WDAS Broadcasting Station, Supreme Court of Pennsylvania (1937). US v. AF of M, District Court (N.D.) Illinois E.b. (1942); Petition for intervention in the AFM case by RCA Victor Division, Radio Corp. of America; Copy of Coll. Agreement Contract for Symphony Orchestra, Columbia Recording Corp.; List of companies that have signed DECCA agreements with AFM; Letter from James C. Petrillo (PRES. AFM) to Davis (Ch. NWLB); Clippings regarding: the Petrillo case
- Notes regarding Case no.111-2499-D, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  "Draft Opinion for the Petrillo Case" (1943) Regarding: Board decision that case may indeed lead to a substantial intelligence with the war effort. This refers to the above case by William A. Waldron. Petrillo is the name of the Pres. of the AFM. "Memo to Mr. William H. Davis regarding: Petrillo Case" (1943) By William A. Waldron. Regarding: position of the parties as to the appropriateness of the Board decision to take jurisdiction over the case; Index of abstract regarding: Electrical Transcriptions (refers to case), Whereas RCA is also engaged in the mfg. and sale of phonograph records, the AFM ban has also affected its members from sewraing RCA thus RCA desires to intervene and become a formal party to the proceedings; "A Committee of the N.A.B." (National Association of Broadcasters 1943, no author). Statement questioning the responsibility of NAB for a press statement released by the Music Sterring Committee, NAB. - "(Unemployment)" (labeled Paul's [Hays] Original Draft) (N.D.) Regarding: unemployment of musicians mechanical reproduction of music as depriving musicians of employment (2 drafts) (N.D.) - 8 pgs. Part of a larger paper, "Small Station Finarices" (ND) (no author) Regarding: financial problems faced by radit co. -"History of Controversy" handwritten in [Paul Hay's] (ND) Regarding: the history of the controversy (2 drafts). -"Jurisdiction of NWLB" handwritten in Paul's 2nd draft discarded- regarding: the jurisdiction of the NWLB - Draft/ Regarding: the employment fund (no date) (no author). - "Memorandum of Conference with Employer Group 10/1/1943" (no author, ND) Regarding: conference request by er after they analyzed the Decca and the Union contract- & list of their objections to the contract.
- Personnel Directory NY State Bd. Of Mediation, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Mss. Draft, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  of case before the NWLB; Western Union Telegraph Co. (NY, NY) vs. American Communications Association, CIO.
- Pub by US DOL BLS, National War Labor Bd., 1922 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  History of its formation and activities, together with its awards and the documentation of importance in the record of its development
- Office of War Mobilization & Recon. Administrative Etc. (W.R. Daulin) carbons and original letters of letters of Myers to various staff members of office of War, Mobilization and Reconversion, 1945-1947 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  regarding: travel arrangements expense reimbursement. Also, 2 receipt booklets "Gov't Requests for Transportation" put out by the Office for Emergency Management NWLB & Office of War Mobilization & Reconversion (OWMR)
- US Conciliation Service Special File (1945-46) letters with attachments (some telegrams), 1945-1946 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  Correspondence between: Meyer & Edgar F. Warren (Director, US Conciliation Service US-DOL), also a few from Meyer's admin. Assistant & Meyers. Regarding: Meyer appointment to Special Advisory Committee Conciliation Service setup, purposes, function; Meyers acceptance to special advisory committee: Maritime disputes (NMU & American Merchant Marine Institute) payment for care work; Case US Steel Corp v. Steelworkers. Attachments regarding: labor-management advisory committee, US Conciliation Service Statement of Labor Policy; Summary of comments by various persons on "Nathan P. Feinsinger Clark Kerr-John E. Roe- Report on the Fact Finding Process;" "Recap of Positions in the Conciliation Service by grade under the present, proposed, and 1947 Budget Organization Plan;" "Minutes of the Advisory Committee to the Director of the US Conciliation Service 1945," Agenda USCS (1945, "Proposed Organization Bureau of Mediation and Arbitration US-DOL; Report of the Committee on Industrial Relations- Resolutional- Conciliation Services."
- National Wage Stab. Bd. General, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  Includes: press release 1946 regarding office move of Reg. Wage Stab. Bd; letter from Meyer to NWSB (1946) requesting payment for all.
- Murray Latimer (?) Meyer to Murray Latimer (OWMR) (position not mentioned), 1945-1946 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  routine correspondence of requests for copies of reports and appointments including telegrams. Also letters regarding study of the steel industry: guaranteed wage plan in the electrical industry, guaranteed wage study organization (such as which industries should be selected for the purpose of reorganization and stabilization studies) aspects; "A proposal for gov't guarantee of er who adopted the annual wage plan;" and as an attachment a copy of the "Guaranteed Wage Plan Study" (ND) (prepared by Latimer). (Official directive emphasizes the connection between guaranteed wage plans and the stabilization of employment and the regularization of production). News Release Form OWMR date, regarding the first installment of the guaranteed wage study.
- Guaranteed Wage (G.W.) General Correspondence. (Literature, books, articles, etc.), 1945-1946 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  Report: "Justification of Budget for study of G.W. plans (1945)," "Application of Income Taxes to Funds Implementing Wage Guarantees (1946)." Correspondence between Meyers and Mat Heineman (VP Franklin Buick Advertising Corp); Paul Joerzog (NWLB); Arthur Jacobs; (Exec. Labor Letter); Thomas McManus (Assistant Counsel Joint Reg. Committee on Industrial and Labor Conditions); NP Feinsinger (Law Professor, U. of Wisconsin); Samuel H. Thompson (Assistant Director, National Planning Assoc.); William H. Davis (Director of Eco. Stab.); Katherine Pollak Fllickson (Assistant Director of Research, CIO) regarding chiefly routine (requesting copies of complements, critiques on articles in magazines, addresses), setting up appointments. Arguments used in the maritime and trucking strikes; industry investigation in respect to the annual wage; study of the steel industry; gov't interest payments: Proctor & Gamble plan. Nunn-Busch Plan- Unites three factors: 1. Payment to worker of a fixed % of volume of business done, 2. Guaranteed min. annual wage, fluctuating with skill level, 3. Overtime work at straight pay to balance hours not worked during the slack period. Also, clippings, bibliography of union agreements guaranteeing employment on annual wage plans
- G.W. Applications for Positions and Related Correspondence, 1945-1946 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  Correspondent: Meyer and various job applicants regarding positions and salary structure.
- Guaranteed Annual Wage, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  Meyer; letters regarding guaranteed wage reports routine- chiefly about receival of report (thank you notes)
- NWLB Administrative and General Matters, Reports, etc. File #2, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  Correspondents: Meyers, George Taylor (NWLB), William A. Waldron (NWLB). Correspondence regarding decision to sign affidavit (affidavit says that if Meyer faces unnecessary pressure to divulge or to procure information in connection with the US War Program- that I'll inform my immediate supervisors of this and notify the investigations office of the Office for Emergency Management). Coal dispute and relationship to the Wage Stab. Program (possible claim under Fair Labor Standards Act under which the dispute can be settled and possible modification of the Little Steel ----- ); Illinois Coal Operators Assoc. v. UMWA agreement and their possible attempt to circumvent the Wage Stab. Policy; Publishers Assoc. of NY regarding Bds. NWLB authority with appointing the arbitrators.
- NWLB Administration and General Matters Reports etc. File #1, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  Letters and telegrams- correspondents: Lloyd Garrison and Meyer Davis, Taylor (1942-43). Correspondence routine regarding personal appointments of Meters to various positions, data, thank you notes informational requests. Also, recommendation of Sidney Cohn as arbitrator to a case Meyer couldn't handle, resignation of position as Assoc. Mb. of the NWLB and appointment as Mb. of the NY Regional War Labor Board; NWLB Decentralization Program; Acceptance letter Meyer (Assoc. Mb. NWLB). Also attached to letters: Resolution on the Title Employees Case before the War Labor Board. Statement regarding Wage Stab. By Industry Relations Committee; Illinois Reg. Assoc. (1943), -Report-NWLB Decentralization Plan (1943). Correspondents include: F.D. Roosevelt, William Davis Ch. NWLB.
- NWLB Wash. Administrative and General, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  Correspondents include: William Brody (Personnel Director NWLB) (1945) and Meyer, Lloyd K. Garrison (Acting Ch. NWLB). Correspondence regarding Official Record of Personnel Action covering appointments with the NWLB; position as Ch. of committee to study the subject of guaranteed wages for the War Mobilization Advisory Bd.; continuation of appointment with NWLB as ad-hoc Panel Ch. with National as opposed to regional.
- [No title], 1943 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  Correspondence concerning routine (bills), receipt of check proposals for --- panel members, NWLB, request for compensation for per diem; Moving Picture Machine Operators Union v. Kingsbridge Theater. Also, rough draft of Hoffman Beverage Company and Drivers and Helper U Inc. reports and recommendation of Hearing Offices and memo of appeals regarding methods of pay.
- 1943-NWLB Compensation, Travel, etc. (Box 2, Folder 16)
  Including routine correspondence of Meyer with various staff of travel authorization Office for Emergency Management vouchers (per diem and subsistence items) and letter stating amount of reimbursements of expenses (treasury checks at one time included with this letter 1943).
- NWLB Fiscal and Travel, 1944-1945 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  Forms: record of official travel; travel authorization (OEM); request for compensation for per diem personnel; vouchers for per diem and/or reimbursement of expenses incident to official travel; vouchers; telegrams; letters regarding claims for reimbursement
- Region II, NWLB, 1944-1945 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  Correspondents include Harry Frumenman (Committee Ch. NWLB); Milton Rubin (Committee Mb. NWLB); William S. Hilger (Sub-Regional Director #9 UAW, CIO); Walter Gellhorn (Regional Vice Ch. NWLB); Maw J. Miller (Assignment Officer, NWLB). Correspondence concerns: investigation of personnel needs of private individual; metal trade rates, City of Lockport; retroactive date in first contract cases, proposed public mbs. (NWLB). Memo release of NWLB moving of offices, also mss. Notes of letter (ND) (no author).
- Waterfront EEs Assn. Series of Additional Cases, File #2, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  letters regarding Waterfront Er's Assoc. of California and International Longshores and Warehouses Union- regarding Board decline of jurisdiction over case to Leonard Berliner, Director, Disputes Division NWLB, from Meyer
- Consolidated Edison (CE) 1942. Consolidated Ed. Of NY vs. International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers and Brotherhood of Consolidated Edison EEs., 1941-1943 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  Report of the Hearing Commission, Collective Bargaining Contract, and memo on behalf of CE of NY with Appendix A Report and findings of Meyer, Hearing Commissioner issues. "Mbs. should receive construction work undertaken by the Co. (a) when the equipment moowed is dead or not connected with an electrical outlet (b) when other building trades are employed," (miss. notes regarding the case).
- Pipe Line Case, 1943-1944 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  Transcontinental pipe lines (nic. The George Bolz Dredging Co., International Hod Carriers, Cominon Laborers Union, International Union of Operating Engineers, United Association of Journeymen Plumbers and Pipe Fitters, Teamsters Preliminary Facts, Dissenting Opinion by Ind. Mb. Issue- G. Bolz Dredging was a sub-contractor employed specifically to construct the Miss. River Crossing (operated strictly on a strictly u basis) (open-shop basis, result picketed and struck creating a conflict during war years)- adjoining Missouri Section was being constructed by Oil States Construction Co. on letters regarding Missouri River Pipeline Crossing, routine matters correspondence between panel mbs. relating to the case. Also, telegrams. Correspondents include: NP Feinsinger (NWLB); Robert H. Zetzman (Colgate-Palmolive Pest Co.); James A. Wilson (International Labor Office); Meyer (1943-1944).
- Firestone Matter 1943 Firestone Tire and Rubber Company (Box 2, Folder 22)
  Includes telegrams and letters (chiefly routine). Also concerns: thoughts underlying primary draft of opinion, elimination of difference in wage rates in fourteen plants, North-South differential continued but not increased, treatment accorded to Memphis regarding u security and right differentials should be the same as other plant. Correspondents include: Lipscomb Davis (Davis Cabinet Co.); Graham H. Anthony (Veeder Root Inc.); Morton Barrisch Vleyer (Mediation Assistant NWLB); Martin Polin (Panel Assistant NWLB). Also, miss. notes referring to the case
- National WLB Personnel and other Matters", 1941-1942 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  forms and cover letter- voucher for per diem and/or reimbursement of expenses incident to travel; request for compensation for per diem personnel. Routine correspondence regarding travel expenses/reimbursement and "standardized gov't travel regulations" 1941 pamphlet chiefly Meyer and various travel clerks and administrative assistants
- Regional War Labor Board, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 24)